Guide to the Houston Folk Music collection, 1972-2017 MS 649
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Houston Folk Music collection
1972-2017
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Doss, Brendan, III
MS 649
1 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
0.02 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0649aip_001 (0.02 GB)
0.007 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0649aip_002 (0.007 GB)
8.32 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0649aip_003 (8.32 GB)
22.1 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0649aip_004 (22.1 GB)
6.08 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0649aip_005 (6.08 GB)
0.011 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0649aip_006 (0.011 GB)
2.56 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0649aip_007 (2.56 GB)
10.2 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0649aip_008 (10.2 GB)
20.9 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0649aip_009 (20.9 GB)
This collection contains items documenting the Houston Folk music scene from the 1970s-1980s.
Biographical / Historical
During the 1960s-1980s, Houston, TX had a vibrant folk scene. Local musicians and those from other parts of Texas and the U.S. socialized and played at a variety of music establishments around the city, including Anderson Fair Retail Restaurant, Sand Mountain Coffeehouse, Liberty Hall, The Old Quarter, Theodore's and Corky's. This scene spawned many musicians, Townes Van Zandt, Guy Clark, Robert Earl Keen, Nanci Griffith, Lynn Langham, Wrecks Bell, Eric Taylor, John Vandiver, Danny Everitt, Vince Bell, Richard Dobson, Don Sanders, Wheatfield/St. Elmo's Fire, Dogtooth Violet, Bill Cade, Lyle Lovett, and many more.
Content Description
This collection contains items documenting the Houston Folk music scene from the 1970s-1980s. More specifically, it has smaller donations of albums, fliers, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This is an artificial collection that has a range of donors.
Related Materials
Please see the Rice University KTRU Radio records, UA 011.
Accruals
Additional materials are expected for this collection.
Index Terms
Subjects
Folk music -- Texas -- Houston; Music
Document Types
Folk-rock music; Folk music
- Series I: Audio
  - "John A. Lomax, Jr. Sings: American Folksongs", 1956 (Box 1)
  - "The Unexpurgated Folk Songs of Men" - Collected by Mack McCormick, 1959 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Tracks include: Side A: "The Ring-A-Rang-A-Roo," "The Keeper of the Eddystone Light," "Mamie Had a Baby," "Cocaine Bill and Morphine Sue," "Take a Whiff On Me," "The Bastard King of England," "No Balls At All," "Barnacle Bill The Sailor," "Big Jim Folsom," "Cristofo Columbo," "The Monk of Priory Hall," "The Hootchy Kootchy Dance," "Always In the Hallway," "In Crawled One-Hung Lo"; Side B: "Whole Stole My Beer?", "Dicky Dido," "Shine and the Titanic," "You Be Kind To Me," "Boar Hog Blues," "Grubbing Hoe," "Uncle Bud," "The Girl I Left Behind Me," "There's A 'Skeeter," "Stavin' Chain," "You Got Good Business," "The Dirty Dozens," "Limericks," "The Ball of Kirriemuir," "Change The Name Of Arkansas!!!"
  - Don Davis and Peter Gardner with Peter Childs and Guy Clark (45 RPM), 1965 (Box 1)
    Tracks include: A: "Brazos," "Little House"; B: "Mail Myself to You," "Nothing at All"
  - Bill Haymes - "USA" (12" LP), 1972 (Box 1)
    Tracks include: A1- "New York City Cowboy; A2- "Taking Leave of the Nest"; A3- Magic; A4- "Just Like You"; A5- "Song for Nita"; B1- "Lounge Lizard's Lament"; B2- "All Our Gardens"; B3- "Barnburning"; B4- "Our Friends the Bears"; B5- "Toward the Attainment of Wisdom"
  - Charlie and Dyanne (12" LP), 1974 (Box 1)
    Tracks include: "I Saw You Again," "Never Was a Rock and Roll Fan," "Dr. Heckle and Mr. Jive," "I'm So Glad You Stayed," "He's Only a Man"
  - Guy Clark - "Old No. 1" (12" LP), 1975; Clark, Guy (Box 1)
    These files are digitized master copy WAVs and access copy MP3s. Tracks include: A1 - "Rita Ballou"; A2 - "L.A. Freeway"; A3 - "She Ain't Goin' Nowhere"; A4 - "Nickel for the Fiddler"; A5 - "That Old Time Feeling"; B1 - "Texas 1947"; B2 - "Desperados Waiting for the Train; B3 - "Like a Coat from the Cold"; B4 - "Instant Coffee Blues"; B5 - "Let Him Roll"
  - "Through the Dark Nightly" (12" LP), 1976; Sanders, Don; Jarrard, Stephen; Cade, Bill; Langham, Lynn; Taylor, Eric; Gorisch, Pete; Russell, Shake (Box 1)
    These files are digitized master copy WAVs and access copy MP3s. Tracks include: A1 - Stephen Jarrard - "Sweet Shine"; A2 - Stephen Jarrard - "Singer in the Sunset"; A3 - Stephen Jarrard - "Pineapple and Rum"; A4 - Don Sanders - "You and Me"; A5 - Don Sanders - "Bayou Song"; A6 - Don Sanders - "Mean Ol' Alcohol"; A7 - Bill Cade - "Ripped Off"; A8 - Bill Cade - "Too Long in the City"; A9 - Bill Cade - "Texas Was My Home"; B1 - Eric Taylor - "Memphis Midnight, Memphis Morning"; B2 - Eric Taylor - "Virginia's Photograph"; B3 - Eric Taylor - "Rainbow & Lightning, Beautiful & Frightening"; B4 - Lynn Langham - "Living in the Music"; B5 - Lynn Langham - "Quickfire"; B6 - Lynn Langham - "Nightdrifts"
  - Townes Van Zandt - "Live at The Old Quarter, Houston, Texas" (double 12" LP), 1977; Van Zandt, Townes; The Old Quarter (Box 1)
    These files are digitized master copy WAVs and access copy MP3s. Track listing: A1 - "Announcement" by Dale Sofar; A2 - "Pancho & Lefty"; A3 - "Mr. Mudd & Mr. Gold"; A4 - "Don't You Take It Too Bad"; A5 - "Two Girls"; A6 - "Fraternity Blues"; A7 - "If I Needed You"; B1 - "Brand New Companion"; B2 - "White Freight Liner Blues"; B3 - "To Live Is to Fly"; B4 - "She Came and She Touched Me"; B5 - "Talking Thunderbird Blues"; B6 - "Rex's Blues"; B7 - "Nine Pound Hammer"; C1 - "For the Sake of the Song"; C2 - "Chauffeur's Blues"; C3 - "No Place to Fall"; C4 - "Loretta"; C5 - "Kathleen"; C6 - "Why She's Acting This Way"; D1 - "Cocaine Blues"; D2 - "Who Do You Love?"; D3 - "Tower Song"; D4 - "Waiting 'Round to Die"; D5 - "Tecumseh Valley"; D6 - "Lungs"; D7 - "Only Him or Me"
  - Nanci Griffith - "there's a light beyond these woods" (12" LP), 1978; Griffith, Nanci (Box 1a)
    These files are digitized master copy WAVs and access copy MP3s. Tracks include: A1 - "I Remember Joe"; A2 - "Alabama Soft Spoken Blues"; A3 - "Michael's Song"; A4 - "Song for Remembered Heroes"; A5 - "West Texas Sun"; B1 - "There's a Light Beyond These Woods"; B2 - "Dollar Matinee"; B3 - "Montana Backroads"; B4 - "John Philip Griffith"
  - Les Doss - "Mysteries" (12" LP), 1985; Doss, Brendan, III (Box 1a)
    These files are digitized master copy WAVs and access copy MP3s. Tracks include: A1 - "Mystic Rose; A2 - "Tryptich - the Four Elements"; A3 - "The Only Waltz There Is"; A4 - "Adoramus Te"; B1 - "Mysteries"; B2 - "Canyon Walls"; B3 - "Solace"; B4 - "Vivace"
  - Nanci Griffith - "Once in a Very Blue Moon" (12" LP), 1985 (Box 1a)
    Contents include: master wav and access mp3s. Tracks include: A1- "Ghost in the Music"; A2- "Live is a Hard Waltz"; A3- "Roseville Fair"; A4- "Mary and Omie"; A5- Friends out in the Madness"; A6- "I'm Not Drivin' These Wheels (Bring the Prose to the Wheel); A7- "Time Alone"; B1- "Ballad of Robin Winter-Smith"; B2- "Daddy Said"; B3- "Once in a Very Blue Moon"; B4- "If I Were the Woman You Wanted"; B5- "Year Down in New Orleans"; B6- "Spin on a Red Brick Floor"
  - Bill Haymes - "Out into the Light" (cassette tape), 1992 (Box 1a)
    Tracks include: Side 1: "Your Whole Surprise," "She Was Just a Girl," "I Need Some Good News Today," "Waiting for Love to Come," "Plateau," "Frozen Somewhere Blues"; Side 2: "Out into the Light," "River Daughter," "I Keep a Certain Distance," "I Flew across the Ocean to Be with You," "Back in the Days When Dinosaurs Ruled the Earth," "Letting Go"
  - The Front Row Reserved Vol. 2, 2006 (Box 1a)
    Key folk tracks include: Dana Cooper - "Empty Glass," Jack Saunders - "I've Got a Thing for You," Nanci Griffith - "Workin' In Corners," Don Sanders - "De Esos Caballos," Sara Hickman - "Two Days Today"
- Series II: General
  - Anderson Fair Retail Restaurant, 1977-2017 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dogtooth Violet and related bands, 1974-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes digital scans of photographs and fliers from the bands Dogtooth Violet, Hickory, Caught in the Act, and Denim. There are access copy jpgs.
  - Ephmera, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fitzgerald's, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - News clippings, 1970s- (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Smith, Reb / Freeborn, 1980
    Contents include: low quality jpg images of the band Freeborn which included Reb Smith, Bill Galbraith, and Vance Whelpy.
  - Spinks, Walter, 1973-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes digital scans of photographs, fliers, and other items that document Anderson Fair Retail Restaurant, Blue Squirrel Corp., and George Ensle. There are access copy jpgs.
  - Van Zandt, Townes lyric book, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wilkerson, Wayne Carnegie Hall stagebill, 1983-11 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Willie the Shake" play, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series III: Oversized
  - Old Quarter poster - The Legacy Clan, 2012-09-30 (Map-drawer 196, Item 2)
  - KPFT Radio Guide, vol. 1, no. 1, 1973-08-01 (Map-drawer 196, Item 3)
  - HFMA celebration posters (7), 2017 (Map-drawer 196, Item 21-23)
  - Wheatfield concert posters (2), 2018 (Map-drawer 196, Item 24)
  - "Going West" - Houston Blacklight and Posters Dist. Co., 1971 (Map-drawer 196, Item 25)
  - "Encounter at Sea" - Houston Blacklight and Posters Dist. Co., 1971 (Map-drawer 196, Item 26)
- Series IV: Video
  - Dana Cooper oral history, 2017-01-20
    These born digital video files consist of one master copy mp4 and one access copy located at scholarship.rice.edu.
  - Rock Romano oral history, 2017-10-25
    These born digital video files consist of one master copy mov and one access copy located at scholarship.rice.edu.
    Conditions Governing Access
    To access the oral history master, request access to this digital material (stored on Fondren Library's nearline / non-public server) by contacting Woodson Research Center staff at woodson@rice.edu. Please use the Identifier number in your request.
  - Homecoming concert video and images, 2017-11-09
    Contents include: an edited mp4 video of the concert and jpgs taken by Jeff Fitlow.
  - Homecoming concert video and images, 2018-11-02
    MS0654aip_007 - Contents include: Images (jpg) and videos (mov) taken by John "Grungy" Gladu of the concert.
    MS0654aip_008 - Contents include: Video (mov) of concert.
  - Judy Weiser oral history, 2018-11-07
    Contents include: mov master oral history and mp4 access version.
  - Lee Jolly oral history, 2019-03-13
    Contents include: mov oral history master and mp4 oral history
  - John Carrick oral history, 2020-04-28; 5.0 Gigabytes
    Contents include: oral history master mov and access mp4
  - Virtual Homecoming concert, 2020-10-29
    Contents include: an mp4, wav, mp3, and txt files related to the virtual Homecoming concert featuring Vince Bell and Sara Hickman.